<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/pessoaTEI.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>English Poems I &amp; II</title>
            <author>
               <rs type="name" key="FP">Fernando Pessoa</rs>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Edição, Codificação</resp>
               <name>Jorge Uribe</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Modelagem de dados, Codificação</resp>
               <name>Ulrike Henny-Krahmer</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Transcrição, Codificação</resp>
               <name>Inês Filipa Rebelo do Carmo</name>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Consultoria</resp>
               <name>Institut für Dokumentologie und Editorik (IDE)</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Universidade Nova de Lisboa, Instituto de Estudos de Literatura e Tradição
               (IELT)</publisher>
            <publisher>Cologne Center for eHumanities (CCeH)</publisher>
            <date>2017</date>
            <availability status="free">
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"/>
            </availability>
            <idno type="filename">Pessoa_English_Poems_I_II.xml</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="genre">
               <rs type="genre" key="poesia">Poesia</rs>
            </note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <list type="work-index">
               <item><rs type="work" key="361">English Poems I &amp; II</rs></item>
            </list>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>English Poems I &amp; II</title>
                  <author>
                     <rs type="name" key="FP">Fernando Pessoa</rs>
                  </author>
                  <textLang mainLang="en"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="1921">1921</date>
                     <pubPlace>Lisboa</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Olisipo ― Apartado 145</publisher>
                     <publisher>Printing Office of the Annuario Commercial ― 24, Restauradores,
                        Lisboa</publisher>
                     <biblScope unit="page">16 pp.</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile xml:base="http://images.cceh.uni-koeln.de/pessoa/">
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_1.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_3.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_5.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_6.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_7.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_8.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_9.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_10.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_11.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_12.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_13.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_14.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_15.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_16.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_17.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_18.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_19.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_20.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_21.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_22.jpg"/>
      <graphic url="Pessoa_English_Poems_23.jpg"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text type="orig" corresp="#W361">
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main" rend="center">ENGLISH POEMS</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub" rend="center">I ― II</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline rend="center">BY<lb/><rs type="name" role="editor" key="FP" style="b">FERNANDO
                  PESSOA</rs>
            </byline>
         </titlePage>
         <div>
            <ab rend="right">OLISIPO</ab>
         </div>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main" rend="center">ENGLISH POEMS</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline rend="center">BY<lb/><rs type="name" role="editor" key="FP" style="b">FERNANDO
                  PESSOA</rs>
            </byline>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="sub" rend="center">I. ― <rs type="name" key="P710"
                  >ANTINOUS</rs><lb/>II. ― INSCRIPTIONS</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <docImprint rend="center">«OLISIPO», APARTADO 145<lb/>1921</docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div>
            <pb/>
            <ab><hi rend="italic">An early and very imperfect draft of</hi>
               <ref target="http://www.pessoadigital.pt/en/pub/Pessoa_Antinous"><rs type="work"
                     key="W323"><rs type="title" key="T361"><rs type="name" key="P710"
                        >Antinous</rs></rs></rs></ref>
               <hi rend="italic">was published in 1918. The present one is meant to annul and
                  supersede that, from which it is essentially different. ―</hi> Inscriptions <hi
                  rend="italic">is now first published. <lb/><metamark rend="line"/><lb/> All rights
                  reserved</hi></ab>
            <ab>Printing Office of the Annuario Commercial<lb/><hi rend="italic">24, Restauradores,
                  Lisbon</hi></ab>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb/>
               <head>I</head>
               <head><rs type="name" key="P710">ANTINOUS</rs></head>
               <lg>
                  <l>The rain outside was cold in <rs type="name" key="P709">Hadrian</rs>'s
                     soul.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The boy lay dead</l>
                  <l>On the low couch, on whose denuded whole,</l>
                  <l>To <rs type="name" key="P709">Hadrian</rs>'s eyes, whose sorrow was a
                     dread,</l>
                  <l>The shadowy light of Death's eclipse was shed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The boy lay dead, and the day seemed a night</l>
                  <l>Outside. The rain fell like a sick affright</l>
                  <l>Of Nature at her work in killing him.</l>
                  <l>Memory of what he was gave no delight,</l>
                  <l>Delight at what he was was dead and dim.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O hands that once had clasped <rs type="name" key="P709">Hadrian</rs>'s warm
                     hands,</l>
                  <l>Whose cold now found them cold!</l>
                  <l>O hair bound estwhile with the pressing bands!</l>
                  <l>O eyes half-diffidently bold!</l>
                  <l>O bare female male-body such</l>
                  <l>As a god's likeness to humanity!</l>
                  <l>O lips whose opening redness erst could touch</l>
                  <l>Lust's seats with a live art's variety!</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="6"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>O fingers skillded in things not to be told!</l>
                  <l>O tongue which, counter-tongued, made the blood bold!</l>
                  <l>O complete regency of lust throned on</l>
                  <l>Raged consciousness's spilled suspension!</l>
                  <l>These things are things that now must be no more.</l>
                  <l>The rain is silent, and the Emperor</l>
                  <l>Sinks by the couch. His grief is like a rage,</l>
                  <l>For the gods take away the life they give</l>
                  <l>And spoil the beauty they made live.</l>
                  <l>He weeps and knows that every future age</l>
                  <l>Is looking on him out of the to-be;</l>
                  <l>His love is on a universal stage;</l>
                  <l>A thousand unborn eyes weep with his misery.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l><rs type="name" key="P710">Antinous</rs> is dead, is dead for ever,</l>
                  <l>Is dead for ever and all loves lament.</l>
                  <l><rs type="name" key="P574" style="b">Venus</rs> herself, that was <rs
                        type="name" key="P612" style="b">Adonis</rs>' lover,</l>
                  <l>Seeing him, that newly lived, now dead again,</l>
                  <l>Lends her old grief's renewal to be blent</l>
                  <l>With <rs type="name" key="P709">Hadrian</rs>'s pain.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now is <rs type="name" key="P604" style="c">Apollo</rs> sad because the
                     stealer</l>
                  <l>Of his white body is for ever cold.</l>
                  <l>No careful kisses on that nippled point</l>
                  <l>Covering his heart-beats' silent place restore</l>
                  <l>His life again to ope his eyes and feel her</l>
                  <l>Presence along his veins Love's fortress hold.</l>
                  <l>No warmth of his another's warmth demands.</l>
                  <l>Now will his hands behind his head no more</l>
                  <l>Linked, in that posture giving all but hands,</l>
                  <l>On the projected body hands implore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The rain falls, and he lies like one who hath</l>
                  <l>Forgotten all the gestures of his love</l>
                  <l>And lies awake waiting their hot return.</l>
                  <l>But all his arts and toys are now with Death.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="7"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>This human ice no way of heat can move;</l>
                  <l>These ashes of a fire no flame can burn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>O <rs type="name" key="P709">Hadrian</rs>, what will now thy cold life be?</l>
                  <l>What boots it to be lord of men and might?</l>
                  <l>His absence o' er thy visible empery</l>
                  <l>Comes like a night,</l>
                  <l>Nor is there morn in hopes of new delight.</l>
                  <l>Now are thy nights widowed of love and kisses;</l>
                  <l>Now are thy days robbed of the night's awaiting;</l>
                  <l>Now have thy lips no purpose for thy blisses,</l>
                  <l>Left but to speak the name that Death is mating</l>
                  <l>With solitude and sorrow and affright.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy vague hands grope, as if they had dropped joy.</l>
                  <l>To hear that the rain ceases lift thy head,</l>
                  <l>And thy raised glance take to the lovely boy.</l>
                  <l>Naked he lies upon that memoried bed;</l>
                  <l>By thine own hand he lies uncoverèd.</l>
                  <l>There was he wont thy dangling sense to cloy,</l>
                  <l>And uncloy whtih more cloying, and annoy</l>
                  <l>Whith newer uncloying till thy senses bled.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His hand and mouth knew games to reinstal</l>
                  <l>Desire that thy worn spine was hurt to follow.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes it seemed to thee that all was hollow</l>
                  <l>In sense in each new straining of sucked lust.</l>
                  <l>Then still new turns of toying would he call</l>
                  <l>To thy nerves' flesh, and thou wouldst tremble and fall</l>
                  <l>Back on thy cushions with thy mind's sense hushed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Beautiful was my love, yet melancholy.</l>
                  <l>He had that art, that makes love captive wholly,</l>
                  <l>Of being slowly sad among lust's rages.</l>
                  <l>Now the Nile gave him up, the eternal Nile.</l>
                  <l>Under this wet locks Death's blue paleness wages</l>
                  <l>Now war upon our wishing with sad smile.»</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Even as he thinks, the lust that is no more</l>
                  <l>Than a memory of lust revives and takes</l>
                  <l>His senses by the hand, his felt flesh wakes,</l>
                  <l>And all becomes again what 'twas before.</l>
                  <l>The dead body on the ned starts up and lives</l>
                  <l>And comes to lie with him, close, closer, and</l>
                  <l>A creeping love-wise and invisible hand</l>
                  <l>At every body-entrance to his lust</l>
                  <l>Whispers caresses which flit off yet just</l>
                  <l>Remain enough to bleed his last nerve's strand,</l>
                  <l>O sweet and cruel Parthian fugitives!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>So he half rises, looking on his lover,</l>
                  <l>That now can love nothing but what none know.</l>
                  <l>Vaguely, half-seeing what he doth behold,</l>
                  <l>He runs his cold lops all the body over.</l>
                  <l>And so ice-senseless are his lips that, lo!,</l>
                  <l>He scarce tastes death from the dead body's cold,</l>
                  <l>But it seems both are dead or living both</l>
                  <l>And love is still the presence and the mover.</l>
                  <l>Then his lips cease on the other lips' cold sloth.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ah, there the wanting breath reminds his lips</l>
                  <l>That from beyond the gods hath moved a mist</l>
                  <l>Between him and this boy. His finger-tips,</l>
                  <l>Still idly searching o'er the body, list</l>
                  <l>For some flesh-response to their waking mood.</l>
                  <l>But their love-question is not understood:</l>
                  <l>The god is dead whose cult was to be kissed!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He lifts his hand up to where heaven should be</l>
                  <l>And cries on the mute gods to know his pain.</l>
                  <l>Let your calm faces turn aside to his plea,</l>
                  <l>O granting powers! He will yield up his reign.</l>
                  <l>In the still deserts he will parchèd live,</l>
                  <pb n="9"/>
                  <l>In the far barbarous roads beggar or slave,</l>
                  <l>But to his arms again the warm boy give!</l>
                  <l>Forego that space ye meant to be his grave!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Take all the female loveliness of earth</l>
                  <l>And in one mound of death its remnant spill!</l>
                  <l>But, by sweet Ganymede, that Jove found worth</l>
                  <l>And above Hebe did elect to fill</l>
                  <l>His cup at his high feasting, and instil</l>
                  <l>The friendlier love that fills the other's dearth,</l>
                  <l>The clod of female embraces resolve</l>
                  <l>To dust, O father of the gods, but spare</l>
                  <l>This boy and his white body and golden hair!</l>
                  <l>Maybe thy better Ganymede thou feel'st</l>
                  <l>That he should be, and out of jealous care</l>
                  <l>From <rs type="name" key="P709">Hadrian</rs>'s arms to thine his beauty
                     steal'st.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He was a kitten playing with lust, playing</l>
                  <l>With his own and with <rs type="name" key="P709">Hadrian</rs>'s, sometimes
                     one</l>
                  <l>And sometimes two, now linking, now undone;</l>
                  <l>Now leaving lust, now lust's high lusts delaying;</l>
                  <l>Now eyeing lust not wide, but from askance</l>
                  <l>Jumping round on lust's half-unexpectance;</l>
                  <l>Now softly gripping, then with fury holding,</l>
                  <l>Now playfully playing, now seriously, now lying</l>
                  <l>By th' side of lust looking at it, now spying</l>
                  <l>Which way to take lust in his lust's withholding.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus did the hours slide from their tangled hands</l>
                  <l>And from their mixèd limbs the moments slip.</l>
                  <l>Now were his arms dead leaves, now iron bands;</l>
                  <l>Now were his lips cups, now the things that sip;</l>
                  <l>Now were his eyes too closed and now too looking;</l>
                  <l>Now were his uncontinuings frenzy working;</l>
                  <l>Now were his arts a feather and now a whip.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>That love they lived as a religion</l>
                  <l>Offered to gods that come themselves to men.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes he was adorned or made to don</l>
                  <l>Half-vestures, then in thatued nudity</l>
                  <l>Did imitate some god that seems to be</l>
                  <l>By marble's accurate virtue men's again.</l>
                  <l>Now was he <rs type="name" key="P574" style="b">Venus</rs>, white out of the
                     seas;</l>
                  <l>And now was he <rs type="name" key="P604" style="c">Apollo</rs>, young and
                     golden;</l>
                  <l>Now as <rs type="name" key="P712">Jove</rs> sate he in mock judgment over</l>
                  <l>The presence at his feet of his slaved lover;</l>
                  <l>Now was he an acted rite, by one beholden,</l>
                  <l>In ever-repositioned mysteries.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now he is something anyone can be.</l>
                  <l>O stark negation of the thing it is!</l>
                  <l>O golden-haired moon-cold loveliness!</l>
                  <l>Too cold! too cold! and love as cold as he!</l>
                  <l>Love through the memories of his love doth roam</l>
                  <l>As through a labyrinth, in sad madness glad,</l>
                  <l>And now calls on his name and bids him come,</l>
                  <l>And now is smiling at his imaged coming</l>
                  <l>That is i'th'heart like faces in the gloaming —</l>
                  <l>Mere shining shadows of the forms they had.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The rain again like a vague pain arose</l>
                  <l>And put the sense of wetness in the air.</l>
                  <l>Suddenly did the Emperor suppose</l>
                  <l>He saw this room and all in it from far.</l>
                  <l>He saw the couch, the boy, and his own frame</l>
                  <l>Cast down against the couch, and he became</l>
                  <l>A clearer presence to himself, and said</l>
                  <l>These words unuttered, sabe to his soul's dread:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The rain again like a vague pain arose</l>
                  <l>And put the sense of wetness in the air.</l>
                  <l>Suddenly did the Emperor suppose</l>
                  <l>He saw this room and all in it from far.</l>
                  <l>HE saw the couch, the boy, and his own frame</l>
                  <l>Cast down against the couch, and he became</l>
                  <l>A clearer presence to himself, and said</l>
                  <l>This words unuttered, sabe to his soul's dread:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«I shall nuild thee a statue that will be</l>
                  <l>To the continued futured evidence</l>
                  <l>Of my love and thy beauty and the sense</l>
                  <l>That beauty giveth of divinity.</l>
                  <pb n="11"/>
                  <l>Though death with subtle uncovering hands remove</l>
                  <l>The apparel of life and empire from our love,</l>
                  <l>Yet its nude statue, that though dost inspirit,</l>
                  <l>All future times, whether they will't or not,</l>
                  <l>Shall, like a gift a forcing god hath brought,</l>
                  <l>Inevitably inherit.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Ay, this thy statue shall I build, and set</l>
                  <l>Upon the pinnacle of being thine, that Time</l>
                  <l>By its subtle dim crime</l>
                  <l>Will fear to eat it from life, or to fret</l>
                  <l>With war's or envy's rage from bulk and stone.</l>
                  <l>Fate cannot be that! Gods themselves, that make</l>
                  <l>Things change, Fate's own hand, that doth overtake</l>
                  <l>The gods themselves with darkness, will draw back</l>
                  <l>From marring thus thy statue and my boon,</l>
                  <l>Leaving the wide world hollow with thy lack.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«This picture of our love will bridge the ages.</l>
                  <l>It will loom white out of the past and be</l>
                  <l>Eternal, like a Roman victory,</l>
                  <l>In every heart the future will give rages</l>
                  <l>Of not being our love's contemporary.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Yet oh that this were needed not, and thou</l>
                  <l>Wert the red flower perfuming my life,</l>
                  <l>The garland on the brows of my delight,</l>
                  <l>The living flame on altars of my soul!</l>
                  <l>Would all this were a thing thou mightest now</l>
                  <l>Smile at from under thy death-moching lids</l>
                  <l>And wonder that I should so put a strife</l>
                  <l>Twixt me and gods for thy lost presence bright;</l>
                  <l>Were there nought in this but my empty dole</l>
                  <l>And thy awakening smile half to condole</l>
                  <l>With what my dreaming pain to hope forbids.»</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="12"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus went he, like a lover who is waiting,</l>
                  <l>From place to place in his dim doubting mind.</l>
                  <l>Now was his hope a great intention fating</l>
                  <l>Its wish to being, now felt he was blind</l>
                  <l>In some point of his seen wish undefined.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When love meets death we know not what to feel.</l>
                  <l>When death foils love we know not what to know.</l>
                  <l>Now did his doubt hope, now did his hope doubt;</l>
                  <l>Now what his wish dreamed the dream's sense did flout</l>
                  <l>And to a sullen emptiness congeal.</l>
                  <l>Then again the gods fanned love's darkening glow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Thy death has given me a higher lust ―</l>
                  <l>A flesh-lust taging for eternity.</l>
                  <l>On mine imperial fate I set my trust</l>
                  <l>That the high gods, that made me emperor be,</l>
                  <l>Will not annul from a more real life</l>
                  <l>My wish that thou should'st live for e'er and stand</l>
                  <l>A fleshly presence on their better land,</l>
                  <l>More lovely yet not lovelier, for there</l>
                  <l>No things impossible our wishes mar</l>
                  <l>Nor pain our hearts with change and time and srtife.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Love, love, my love! thou art already a god.</l>
                  <l>This thought of mine, which I a wish believe,</l>
                  <l>Is no wish, but a sight, to me allowed</l>
                  <l>By the great gods, that love love and can give</l>
                  <l>To mortal hearts, under the shape of wishes ―</l>
                  <l>Of wishes having undiscovered reaches ―,</l>
                  <l>A vision of the real things beyond</l>
                  <l>Our life-imprisoned life, our sense-bound sense.</l>
                  <l>Ay, what I wish thee to be thou art now</l>
                  <l>Already. Already on Olympic ground</l>
                  <l>Thou walkest and art perfect, yet art thou,</l>
                  <l>For thou needst no excess of thee to don</l>
                  <l>Perfect to be, being perfection.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>«My heart is singing like a morning bird.</l>
                  <l>A great hope from the gods comes down to me</l>
                  <l>And bids my heart to subtler sense be stirred</l>
                  <l>And think not that strange evil of thee</l>
                  <l>That to think thee mortal would be.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«My love, my love, my god-love! Let me kiss</l>
                  <l>On thy lips thy hot lips now immortal,</l>
                  <l>Greeting thee at Death's portal's happiness,</l>
                  <l>For to the gods Death's portal is Life's portal.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Were no Olympus yet for thee, my love</l>
                  <l>Would make thee one, where thou sole god mightst prove,</l>
                  <l>And I thy sole adorer, glad to be</l>
                  <l>Thy sole adorer through infinity.</l>
                  <l>That were a universe divine enough</l>
                  <l>For love and me and what to me though art.</l>
                  <l>To have thee is a thing made of gods' stuff</l>
                  <l>And too look on thee eternity's best part.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«But this is true and mine own art: the god</l>
                  <l>Thou art now is a body made by me,</l>
                  <l>For, is thou art now flesh reality</l>
                  <l>Beyond where men age and night cometh still,</l>
                  <l>'Tis to my love's great making power thou owest</l>
                  <l>That life thou on the memory bestowest</l>
                  <l>And mak'st it carnal. Had my love not held</l>
                  <l>An empire of my mighty legioned will,</l>
                  <l>Thou to gods' consort hadst not been compelled.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«My love that found thee, when it found thee did</l>
                  <l>But find its own true body and exact look.</l>
                  <l>Therefore when now thy memory I bid</l>
                  <l>Become a god where gods are, I but move</l>
                  <l>To death's high column's top the shape it took</l>
                  <l>And set it there for vision of all love.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="14"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>«O love, my love, put up with my strong will</l>
                  <l>Of loving to Olympus, be thou there</l>
                  <l>The latest god, whose honey-coloured hair</l>
                  <l>Takes divine eyes! As thou wert on earth, still</l>
                  <l>In heaven bodifully be and roam,</l>
                  <l>A prisoner of that happiness of home,</l>
                  <l>With elder gods, while I on earth do make</l>
                  <l>A statue for thy deathlessness' seen sake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Yet thy true deathless statue I shall build</l>
                  <l>Will be no stone thing, but that same regret</l>
                  <l>By which our love's eternity is willed.</l>
                  <l>One side of that is thou, as gods see thee</l>
                  <l>Now, and the other, here, thy memory.</l>
                  <l>My sorrow will make that men's god, and set</l>
                  <l>Thy naked memory on the parapet</l>
                  <l>That looks upon the seas of future times.</l>
                  <l>Some will say all our love was but our crimes;</l>
                  <l>Others against our names the knives will whet</l>
                  <l>Of their glad hate of beauty's beauty, and make</l>
                  <l>Our names a base of heap whereon to rake</l>
                  <l>The names of all our brothers with quick scorn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet will our presence, like eternal Morn,</l>
                  <l>Ever return at Beauty's hour, and shine</l>
                  <l>Out of the East of Love, in light to enshrine</l>
                  <l>New gods to come, the lacking world to adorn.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«All that thou art now is thyself and I.</l>
                  <l>Our dual presence has its unity</l>
                  <l>In that perfection of body which my love,</l>
                  <l>By loving it, became, and did from life</l>
                  <l>Raise into godness, calm above the strife</l>
                  <l>Of times, and changing passions far above.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«But since men see more with the eyes that soul,</l>
                  <l>Still I in stone shall utter this great dole;</l>
                  <l>Still, eager than men hunger by thy presence,</l>
                  <pb n="15"/>
                  <l>I shall to marble carry this regret</l>
                  <l>That in my heart like a great star is set.</l>
                  <l>Thus, even in stone, ourl love shall stand so great</l>
                  <l>In thy statue of us, like a god's fate,</l>
                  <l>Our love's incarnate and discarnate essence,</l>
                  <l>That, like a trumpet reaching over seas</l>
                  <l>And going from continent to continent,</l>
                  <l>Our love shall speak its joy and woe, death-blent,</l>
                  <l>Over infinities and eternities</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«And here, memory or statue, we shall stand,</l>
                  <l>Still the same one, as we were hand in hand</l>
                  <l>Nor felt each other's hand for feeling feeling.</l>
                  <l>Men still will see me when thy sense they take.</l>
                  <l>The entire gods might pass, in the vast wheeling</l>
                  <l>Of the globed ages. If but for thy sake,</l>
                  <l>That, being theirs, hadst gone with their gone band,</l>
                  <l>They would return, as they had slept to wake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>«Then the end of days when <rs type="name" key="P712">Jove</rs> were born
                     again</l>
                  <l>And <rs type="name" key="P711">Ganymede</rs> again pour at his feast</l>
                  <l>Would see our dual soul from death released</l>
                  <l>And recreated unto joy, fear, pain —</l>
                  <l>All that love doth contain;</l>
                  <l>Life — all the beauty that doth make a lust</l>
                  <l>Of love's own true love, at the spell amazed;</l>
                  <l>And, if our very memory wore to dust,</l>
                  <l>By some gods' race of the end of ages must</l>
                  <l>Our dual unity again be raised».</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It rained still. But slow-treading night came in,</l>
                  <l>Closing the weary eyelids of each sense.</l>
                  <l>The very consciousness of self and soul</l>
                  <l>Grew, like a landscape through dim raining, dim.</l>
                  <l>The Emperor lay still, so still that now</l>
                  <l>He half forgot where now he lay, or whence</l>
                  <l>The sorrow that was still salt on his lips.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="16"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>All had been something very far, a scroll</l>
                  <l>Rolled up. The things he felt were like the rim</l>
                  <l>That haloes rould the moon when the night weeps.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His head was bowed into his arms, and they</l>
                  <l>On the low couch, foreign to his sense, lay.</l>
                  <l>His closed eyes seemed open to him, and seeing</l>
                  <l>The naked floor, dark, cold, sad and unmeaning.</l>
                  <l>His hurt breath was all his sense could know.</l>
                  <l>Out of the falling darkness the wind rose</l>
                  <l>And fell; a voice swooned in the courts below;</l>
                  <l>And the Emperor slept.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l rend="indent">The gods came now</l>
                  <l>And bore something away, no sense knows how,</l>
                  <l>On unseen arms of power and repose.</l>
               </lg>
               <ab>Lisbon, 1915.</ab>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="17"/>
               <head>II</head>
               <head>INSCRIPTIONS</head>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>I</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We pass and dream. Earth smiles. Virtue is rare.</l>
                     <l>Age, duty, gods weigh on our conscious bliss.</l>
                     <l>Hope for the best and for the worst prepare.</l>
                     <l>Tha sum of purposed wisdom speaks in this.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>II</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Me, Chloe, a maid, the mighty fates have given,</l>
                     <l>Who was nought to them, to the people shades.</l>
                     <l>Thus the gods will. My years were but twice seven.</l>
                     <l>I am forgotten in my distant glades.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>III</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>From my villa on the hill I long looked down</l>
                     <l>Upon the muttering town;</l>
                     <l>Then one day drew (life sight-sick, dull hope shed)</l>
                     <l>My toga o'er my head</l>
                     <l>(The simplest gesture being the greatest thing)</l>
                     <l>Like a raised wing.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <pb n="18"/>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>IV</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Not Cecrops kept my bees. My olives bore</l>
                     <l>Oil like the sun. My several herd lowed far.</l>
                     <l>The breathing traveller rested by my door.</l>
                     <l>The wet earth smells still; dead my nostrils are.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>V</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I conquered. Far barbarians hear my name.</l>
                     <l>Men were dice in my game,</l>
                     <l>But to throw myself did lesser come:</l>
                     <l>I threw dice, Fate the sum.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>VI</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Some were as loved loved, some as prizes prized.</l>
                     <l>A natural wife to the fed man my mate,</l>
                     <l>I was sufficient to whom I sufficed.</l>
                     <l>I moved, slept, bore and aged without a fate.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>VII</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I put by pleasure like an alien bowl.</l>
                     <l>Stern, separate, mine, I looked towards where gods seem.</l>
                     <l>From behind me the common shadow stole.</l>
                     <l>Dreaming that I slept not, I slept my dream.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>VIII</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Scarce five years passed ere I passed too.</l>
                     <l>Death came and took the child he found.</l>
                     <l>No god spared, or fate smiled at, so</l>
                     <l>Small hands, clutching so little round.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <pb n="19"/>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>IX</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>There is a silence where the town was old.</l>
                     <l>Grass grows shere not a memory lies below.</l>
                     <l>We that dined loud are sand. The tale is told.</l>
                     <l>The far hoofs hush. The inn's last light doth go.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>X</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>We, that both lie here, loved. This denies us.</l>
                     <l>My lost hand crumbles where her breasts' lack is</l>
                     <l>Love's known, each lover is anonymous.</l>
                     <l>We both felt fair. Kiss, for that was our kiss.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>XI</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I for my city's want far and fell.</l>
                     <l>I could not tell</l>
                     <l>What she did want, that knew she wanted me.</l>
                     <l>Her walls be free,</l>
                     <l>Her speech keep such as I spoke, and men die,</l>
                     <l>That she die not, as I.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>XII</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Life lived us, not we life. We, as bees sip,</l>
                     <l>Looked, talked and had. Trees grow as we did last.</l>
                     <l>We loved the gods but as we see a ship.</l>
                     <l>Never aware of being aware, we passed.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>XIII</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The work is done. The hammer is laid down.</l>
                     <l>The artisans, that built the slow-grown town,</l>
                     <l>Have been succeeded by those who still built.</l>
                     <pb n="20"/>
                     <l>All this is something lack-of-something screening.</l>
                     <l>The thought whole has no meaning</l>
                     <l>But lies by Time's wall like a pitcher spilt.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="poem">
                  <head>XIV</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This covers, that erst had the blue sky.</l>
                     <l>This soil treads me, that once I trod. My hand</l>
                     <l>Put these inscriptions here, half knowing why;</l>
                     <l>Last, and hence seeing all, of the passing band.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <ab>Lisbon, 1920.</ab>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
